<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.3.2">Jekyll</generator><link href="http://localhost:4000/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="http://localhost:4000/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2023-11-25T16:11:26+01:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/feed.xml</id><title type="html">Open Tech</title><subtitle>I wonder the world seeking the beauty in systems and patterns, natural or man-made...</subtitle><entry><title type="html">Weird issue with multiprocessing in python…at scale</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/experiments/2023/11/10/weird-bug.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Weird issue with multiprocessing in python…at scale" /><published>2023-11-10T23:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2023-11-10T23:00:00+01:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/experiments/2023/11/10/weird-bug</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/experiments/2023/11/10/weird-bug.html"><![CDATA[<h1 id="context">Context</h1>

<p>For several weeks now, I’ve been working on building a simple game, to test ideas and emergent behaviors from agents learning playing a game. The learning is done by either evolutionary algorithms (the current status) or probably later down the road, reinforcement learning.</p>

<p>My stack is simple: <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">python-arcade</code> for the game development, <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">pygmo</code> for the evolutionary algorithms, and <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">pytorch</code> for the neural networks.</p>

<p>The first game is a proof of concept: two agents, one of them has to shoot the other. Each agent is controlled by a neural network, and the neural network is trained using evolutionary algorithms. Both agents use the same neural network. For the sake of simplicity, the neural network takes as input the position of both agents, and outputs the action to take (move forward, fire…etc).</p>

<h1 id="the-problem">The problem</h1>

<p>For several weeks now, there was a stagnation in my progress. A big reason for this was the a problem that happened after nearly ~1800*32 evaluation times: the optimization program just freezes.</p>

<p>To describe what happens, there is class holding the problem: evaluate the quality of a solution (in this case, a neural network that represent the tank policy), by playing 32 games (the number of cores I’ve available), and measure the average score. The 32 games are played in parallel, thanks to the <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">multiprocessing</code> library in python.</p>

<p>The parallel evaluation exists inside the class, something like this:</p>

<div class="language-python highlighter-rouge"><div class="highlight"><pre class="highlight"><code><span class="c1"># A snipped from the problem class
</span><span class="k">class</span> <span class="nc">Problem</span><span class="p">:</span>
    <span class="k">def</span> <span class="nf">evaluate</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="n">self</span><span class="p">,</span> <span class="n">solution</span><span class="p">):</span>
        <span class="c1"># ...
</span>        <span class="k">with</span> <span class="n">multiprocessing</span><span class="p">.</span><span class="nc">Pool</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="n">processes</span><span class="o">=</span><span class="mi">32</span><span class="p">)</span> <span class="k">as</span> <span class="n">pool</span><span class="p">:</span>
            <span class="n">results</span> <span class="o">=</span> <span class="n">pool</span><span class="p">.</span><span class="nf">map</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="n">worker</span><span class="p">,</span> <span class="nf">range</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="mi">32</span><span class="p">))</span>
        <span class="c1"># ...
</span></code></pre></div></div>
<p>where the <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">worker</code> is basically a game run.</p>

<p>The issue is that after a while, the whole thing just freezes. The 32 processes are still running, but they are not doing anything. The CPU usage is idle. The memory usage is idle. The processes are still alive, but they are not doing anything. They are just stuck.</p>

<p>This kind of problems is probably the most annoying kind: a ghost in the wires. There are no traces that I can find of why there is a problem, and it is difficult to reproduce.</p>

<p>Without better information, I went through a process of elimination: I started with the <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">pygmo</code> optimization library. So, I built a small optimization library from scratch, with a couple of algorithms, benchmarked them, and then used it instead. Yet, the problem persisted.</p>

<p>I tried to use a <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">signal</code> to kill the processes after a certain time, but the problem persisted.</p>

<p><em>I then accidentally moved the <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">with multiprocessing.Pool(processes=32) as pool</code> part outside the class, and the problem disappeared. I thought it was a coincidence, but it wasn’t. The problem was gone.</em></p>

<h1 id="why-is-that">Why is that?</h1>

<p>After asking chatgpt, it seems that the use of the <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">multiprocessing</code> library inside a class implies that the class will have to pickled and unpickled. The pickled class is passed to the new processes. This can lead to unexpected behavior or even deadlocks if the class state cannot be pickled or if it has side effects when pickled and unpickled.</p>

<p>By moving the <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">multiprocessing</code> part outside the class, there is no need to pickle the class, and the problem is gone.</p>

<p>According to ChatGPT, to avoid pickling issues in python, the advice is:</p>
<ol>
  <li>Use top-level functions: Functions that are defined at the top level of a module are easier to pickle and unpickle. Avoid using lambda functions or functions defined inside other functions or methods.</li>
  <li>Avoid non-picklable objects: Some objects cannot be pickled, including open file or network connections, threads, processes, stack frames, deeply recursive classes, and others. If you need to share such objects between processes, consider using a server process or file-based sharing.</li>
</ol>

<p>…I hope this is right.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="experiments" /><category term="programming" /><category term="bug" /><category term="evolutionary algorithms" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Context]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Thoughts on management, from the recent OpenAI announcement</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/thinking/2023/11/07/reflection-from-openai.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Thoughts on management, from the recent OpenAI announcement" /><published>2023-11-07T23:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2023-11-07T23:00:00+01:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/thinking/2023/11/07/reflection-from-openai</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/thinking/2023/11/07/reflection-from-openai.html"><![CDATA[<p>Recently OpenAI made an announcement about new changes to their products: new models, lower pricing, better performance, more desperately needed features.</p>

<p>Maybe it was just a particular timing, but it did hit me hard the quality and the clarity of the communication. It was product management at its finest.</p>

<p>It is sometimes difficult to understand or appreciate the amount of effort required to control the of entropy that exists within a team, let alone multiple teams. It is not because it is hard, but because it so simple, yet somehow it escapes most people’s.</p>

<p>It is always easier to over-complexify things. Complexity creates obscurity, and obscurity creates confusion, and most of the people flourish in confusion. Lots of jobs are being created are dependent on confusion. A positive feedback loop is created, and the system is self-sustaining. Lots of talents are being wasted in this process.</p>

<p>I can’t count how many times we have been through this: There should be one person orchestrating the project, instead of multiple people with unclear responsibilities and overlapping roles. The teams must be aligned vertically and horizontally: alignment between the single team members, and between different teams. The communication must be clear and concise: not tens of pages of fluff (keep that for the person in charge only, not for everyone to interpret on their own), but a single page of clear and concise communication. Managers must have the mandate and the clear allocation of resources, and they must be held accountable for the results.</p>

<p>It is strange but, nothing of what OpenAI mentioned was new. We all knew what needed to be done, and most of it could have been done without OpenAI (except the model improvements perhaps), yet, no one did it. Not even OpenAI competitors.</p>

<p>I realize that this maybe an emotional rant, and probably reality is a bit different than what I am describing, but I don’t think I missed reality by a lot.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="thinking" /><category term="reflection" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Recently OpenAI made an announcement about new changes to their products: new models, lower pricing, better performance, more desperately needed features.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Evolutionary Algorithms for Games - Part 1</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/thinking/2023/10/27/ea-copy.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Evolutionary Algorithms for Games - Part 1" /><published>2023-10-27T00:00:00+02:00</published><updated>2023-10-27T00:00:00+02:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/thinking/2023/10/27/ea%20copy</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/thinking/2023/10/27/ea-copy.html"><![CDATA[<p>This is the start of a diary to record my work and progress in this</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="thinking" /><category term="evolutionary algorithms" /><category term="games" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[This is the start of a diary to record my work and progress in this]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Reflections on Programming</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/thinking/2023/10/27/novice-mistakes.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Reflections on Programming" /><published>2023-10-27T00:00:00+02:00</published><updated>2023-10-27T00:00:00+02:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/thinking/2023/10/27/novice-mistakes</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/thinking/2023/10/27/novice-mistakes.html"><![CDATA[<p>There is a deep love that is hard to understand or express: the simplicity and purity of the relationship, sound of keyboard, the feeling of control, the gratification of the outcome, the challenge of the puzzle, the room for improvement, the patience of the machine…</p>

<p>I have been programming for more than 20 years, and I still feel like a novice. I still feel like I am learning the basics. I still feel like I am learning how to learn. I still feel like I am learning how to think.</p>

<p>This is merely a reflection on an activity I deeply love and cherish.</p>

<h2 id="young-dreams----2003">Young dreams (? - 2003)</h2>
<p>I was dreaming about coding. I really liked the idea of having a conversation with the machine: It felt like a mix of gratification of control, and the honesty of the feedback. I was reading stories about hackers and programmers, but it felt very unclear how to reach that, or where to start.</p>

<h2 id="troublesome-beginnings-2003---2008">Troublesome beginnings (2003 - 2008)</h2>
<p>I managed to put my hands on a arabic book on <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">Visual Basic 6</code>, which was really exciting. But,…where is visual basic exactly? 
I was already pretty good with Microsoft word at that time. Unfortunately, it was offering some sort of <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">visual basic</code> macros - if my memory serves me right -. For a while, I thought this is where Visual Basic is. I tried a lot to make it work, but it didn’t. I was very disappointed.</p>

<p>It is important to understand the context here: I couldn’t read in English back then. The resources in Arabic was really scarce. There was no community or anyone to talk to. I was new to the internet, but what can be done with the internet was still work in progress. There were no libraries you just go to in order to buy book.</p>

<p>Then, a breakthrough happened in 2003: a colleague in my class happened to have been programming for a while (the first and last person I meet during my school years who did any programming). He gave me a copy of <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">Microsoft Visual Studio 6</code>, and Voila!! I was in.
But with this amazing gift came a bad curse: he advised me to change to <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">C++</code> instead, since it is a much more powerful language. And I didn’t waste any time: I set sail to <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">C++</code>.</p>

<p>One of the first books I picked was <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">C++ in 21 days</code>. I decided that English is the way to go. I spent over 6 months, progressing 1 page a day, translating word by word, just to realize that the sentence doesn’t mean much to me. My dad also believed in using a traditional dictionary instead of an electronic one, which made the process even more painful. I was really struggling, but I was determined to make it work. And it worked.</p>

<p>I also found a couple of other books in arabic. One book, the deeply touched me, was for a Saudi engineer (I can’t for the life of me find any traces of him). At that time, pirated books was the only available way. However, that guy put his book online for free, and asked that if you like his book, to buy it. It was such a revolutionary idea, I was really touched by it. I never knew how to buy the book though. I would still love to buy it.</p>

<p>With English unlocked, and these few precious arabic resources, rapid progress was made: I could do all the basic things in <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">C++</code>. I can’t count how many times I built a calculator.</p>

<p>But then what? Here was the curse. I actually didn’t know what to do. My fantasies when I started programming was hacking mainly and building games. Now, what do I do with that syntax?
The road to making simple games was probably more feasible with <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">Visual Basic</code>, but the wall was pretty damn high with <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">C++</code> (I didn’t realize it that time). 
My solution was: study more books about <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">C++</code>. Not very long after, my advance has stagnated, and I was stuck.</p>

<h2 id="the-first-breakthrough-2008---2010">The first breakthrough (2008 - 2010)</h2>
<p>I took an electronics course in the summer of 2008, where we learned to program micro-controllers. I was already familiar with the <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">C</code> language, which made this part of the course easy for me, but most importantly, it gave me a meaning: I can write a piece of code that will turn a LED on and off! It was a crazy powerful idea! I can…do things! And it was not far fetched to imagine doing useful things to me.</p>

<p>After that course, I built a lot of small programs for micro-controllers, went for multiple large projects (robots mainly). It was fun and painful in the same time Working with micro-controllers means working with hardware, which is a tough cookie though: it is expensive, and debugging is hard. But it was a lot of fun.</p>

<p>I took a course on <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">assembly</code> for <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">x86</code> back then, which was oddly satisfying. It did reinforce a certain idea that was building up: I like working close to the metal. High levels of abstraction didn’t appeal to me that much.</p>

<h2 id="the-second-breakthrough-2011---2013">The second breakthrough (2011 - 2013)</h2>
<p>Necessity dictated that I put an end to my projects with micro-controllers:</p>

<ul>
  <li>They were expensive, and I personally couldn’t afford the electronics part</li>
  <li>I loved mixing electronics was mechanics, which was far more expensive and complex.
    <ul>
      <li>I was already suffering from multiple failures in orchestrating projects with people from mechanical engineering.</li>
    </ul>
  </li>
  <li>There were barely any electronics in Egypt: sensors, motors, wireless modules, etc. were very hard, if not completely unavailable, to find.</li>
  <li>A multimeter will only get you so far. Without access to an oscilloscope, debugging was a nightmare.</li>
</ul>

<p>It was survival time. Thanks to the strategic insight from a dear friend (Moustafa Kassem), we started working on a project on FPGA. I shifted to <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">Verilog</code>, which is a language to describe hardware elements and the connections between them. The beauty of the setup at the time was that it removed all complex elements: access to hardware wasn’t required for the vast majority of the time, and simulators would do just fine.</p>

<p>I loved <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">verilog</code>, the setup, everything related to computer architecture, but the projects were not fun at all. They were…the right and responsible thing to do. I tried to find fun in pockets inside the projects (architecture, module design, code quality, etc.), but it was not the same. My heart was not in it.</p>

<p>One interesting thing during those years is that I still didn’t understand most of the concepts that student in computer engineering were taught in programming courses. For me, everything was a <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">Finite State Machine</code>.</p>

<p>Doing the right things though paid off very well: I got a couple of very lucrative jobs offers before I graduated.</p>

<p>My work in Siemens was a continuation of these projects. It was stimulating to see high quality code and patterns from more experienced engineers. I learned a lot.</p>

<p>But then, I stumbled upon this weird language: <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">Perl</code>, which was used to build parsers, as part of our verification environment. I damn loved <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">Perl</code> and <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">regular expressions</code>. I read a couple of books, did so many small programs. I was pretty good at reading all this alien-like notations.</p>

<p>But, most importantly, I had use-cases: automating parts of my work.</p>

<p>For example, when we run the regressions test-cases, we needed to fill an excel sheet with the results of each test-case. And boy I sucked at this! So, I wrote a script that would parse the log files, and fill the excel sheet for me, with colors and stats and everything. It was amazing! I was hooked.
I built a system to generate more complex test-cases (back then, we were writing the test-cases manually, following an agreed upon verification plan). Found 3 critical bugs before the release. Neat! The project manager was very happy, and he presented it to the department director. It was awesome!</p>

<p><code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">Perl</code> was just the right level of abstraction, in the right time, with the right problems. I love it to this day.</p>

<p>My love for <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">verilog</code> fading away. I always wanted to build a microprocessor. I found that book about a demonstration processor called <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">Vespa</code></p>

<p>Back then, I read a couple of books that had a great impact on me:</p>
<ul>
  <li><code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">Automate this: How algorithms came to rule our world</code></li>
  <li><code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">The Age of Spiritual Machines: When Computers Exceed Human Intelligence</code></li>
</ul>

<p>This encouraged me to do <em>Andrew Ng</em>’s famous course on <em>Machine Learning</em></p>

<h2 id="hard-reset-2014">Hard reset (2014)</h2>
<p>I started a MSc in embedded systems in Switzerland, but two months in, it was clear that my heart and mind is in Artificial Intelligence. I applied for another MSc in France, in ML, got accepted.
There were ~6 months until I started the MSc. Since I don’t come from a CS background, and my math (statistics in particular) wasn’t up to the task, I decided to take the time to invest in online courses, address my weak points, and prepare for the MSc.</p>

<p>One course in particular I tried to do many times a year earlier, and failed consistently, was Algorithms course from Stanford. Every time I made an excuse: I was too busy, the stars were not aligned, …etc.
This time, I was adamant to get it right. I even blamed the course itself.
So, a similar course, but from Princeton, was starting. I was determined to get it right this time. First week was brutal, I struggled a lot. Second week, I was working day and night, I simply couldn’t finish.</p>

<p>There was this shocking realization that…I am not good at programming in the first place.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="thinking" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[There is a deep love that is hard to understand or express: the simplicity and purity of the relationship, sound of keyboard, the feeling of control, the gratification of the outcome, the challenge of the puzzle, the room for improvement, the patience of the machine…]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">French Journey - Part 3</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/thinking/2023/09/24/french-journey-part-3.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="French Journey - Part 3" /><published>2023-09-24T00:00:00+02:00</published><updated>2023-09-24T00:00:00+02:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/thinking/2023/09/24/french-journey-part-3</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/thinking/2023/09/24/french-journey-part-3.html"><![CDATA[<ul>
  <li><a href="/data-science/machine-learning/nlp/2022/02/15/french-journey-part-1.html">Part 1</a></li>
  <li><a href="/data-science/machine-learning/nlp/2022/08/19/french-journey-part-2.html">Part 2</a></li>
</ul>

<p>This whole journey started out for very different objectives (analyzing the political scene in France), and then it progressed forward, out of curiosity.</p>

<p>In the previous parts, I presented preliminary results of the results of the analysis of nearly 1.5 million articles from <a href="http://www.lemonde.fr">LeMonde</a>, and <em>I extracted the most frequently used 80% of French words, which was nearly 2600 words</em>. I came to realize that it might be useful to solve my problem in learning French.</p>

<p>The main difficulty in such situations is to design a process to distill these desires and assets into clear requirements, using available tools, in order to produce actionable habits. This is often a non-linear phase. After that comes the assembly part: acquire (or build) all these pieces and put them together. Then, reality check: let’s use it for a while. Iterations and feedbacks are the keys of the game: the faster, the better. And through all of this, there is a deep imposter syndrome and flying demons everywhere.</p>

<p>To learn French using my previous findings, my initial thoughts were:</p>
<ol>
  <li>Memorize the individual words using flashcards</li>
  <li>Learn in context:
    <ol>
      <li>(Passive) Reading: I used an optimization system to find the best set of articles from LeMonde, that would allow me to see every one of those selected words, in context, at least 10 times. This resulted in a set of ~400 articles.</li>
      <li>(Active) Writing: Similar to reading, the objective was to deliberately write sentences/paragraphs that will lead to ~10 times repetition of each word.</li>
    </ol>
  </li>
</ol>

<p>This article describes my experience so far. Once all the pieces were in place, I gave myself 2 months to try them all on daily bases.</p>

<p>Before we start, I think it is important to give on the context on why my motives, and the challenges I faced that drove me there:</p>
<ol>
  <li>I would love to learn French
    <ol>
      <li>To get better at integrating with the society</li>
      <li>To unlock this the doors for this massive culture</li>
      <li>Because I believe that being accustomed to ignorance is contagious to other aspects of life</li>
    </ol>
  </li>
  <li>Despite many attempts, I could not find a suitable language course: either it was too expensive, course hours were inconvenient (in the middle of the working hours), or unsuitable medium (I really didn’t like courses over zoom). With no course, there is no curriculum / gradual steps</li>
  <li>I don’t have a natural stress to learn French
    <ol>
      <li>My work was / is / likely will be in English.</li>
      <li>All my French friends speak perfect English.</li>
      <li>A lot of French people speak English just fine.</li>
    </ol>
  </li>
  <li>I don’t watch TV (which is ironic: I always thought that was a great thing, but in this case, it is a massive weakness).</li>
</ol>

<p>Simply speaking: It’s a matter of numbers, and I don’t have the proper context to do the numbers.</p>

<h1 id="experience">Experience</h1>

<h2 id="learning-individual-words">Learning individual words</h2>

<p>I formatted and uploaded all the extracted words and their translations to <a href="https://apps.ankiweb.net/">Anki</a>, a powerful flashcard app. The results were immediate, tangible, and amazing!</p>

<p>At the beginning, I started with learning 100 new words a day, and reviewing 200 more (since I already know many words). As I progressed (after ~700 new words), the rhythm changed to 50 new words and review about 100.</p>

<p>There has been a direct improvement in my conversation and reading skills: I am able to use a wider range of vocabulary to express myself and my point of view. When I am stuck, I have a larger toolbox to choose from.</p>

<p>The transition from extracted words to flashcards was “almost” seamless:</p>
<ol>
  <li>One-to-one translation between French and English sometimes didn’t capture the meaning.
    <ol>
      <li>Many French words map to the same English word, but if you look at the French dictionary, there can be subtle or important differences in meaning.</li>
    </ol>
  </li>
  <li>A few entities (such as some people’s names) have escaped my processing pipeline, which further required cleaning.</li>
</ol>

<p>This required cleaning, consolidation of words, and compromises, which resulted in approximately 400 word entries being removed.</p>

<p>Certain words, such as propositional letters, were challenging to learn, and still are. This indicated that a larger context, such as a phrase, and perhaps more modalities (i.e., listening and writing) may help in the learning these words.</p>

<h1 id="next-steps">Next steps</h1>

<h2 id="words-and-reading">Words and Reading</h2>

<p>The next frontier is to ground these words with reading and writing. For the reading part, a friend tried generating example phrases using ChatGPT for the new words he is learning in german. Naturally, I wanted to try the same.</p>

<p>With simple prompts, I was able to:</p>

<ol>
  <li>
    <p>Extract the new words from any text</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>Generate 3 example phrases for any word I want, and their translations.</p>
    <ol>
      <li>If the word is a verb, then generate 3 phrases for each tense (upping the game now).</li>
    </ol>
  </li>
</ol>

<p>And then it was easy to parse the words and sentences, and add them to Anki as flashcards.</p>

<p>The idea is to generate a replacement for the LeMonde articles, while maintaining the objective of being focused. In other words, I wanted to generate the <strong><em>minimum viable book for the learning french language</em></strong>.</p>

<p>I have just built the pipeline to do so, and generated the flashcards. You can find:</p>

<ul>
  <li>
    <p><a href="https://dashboard.osm-ai.net/">A website I created so you can try that yourself</a></p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p><a href="https://github.com/osm3000/LangLearnCopilot">The Github for the package with more tools to build your own flashcards</a></p>
  </li>
</ul>

<p>The Anki words will continue to be part of my practice, with incremental increase of new words that I encounter. There are already many new words in the phrases generated by GPT 😄</p>

<p>An alternative plan would be to use such a system for problematic words only (e.g., I am struggling with proposition letters, thus, it makes more sense to have a concentrated reading examples), while investing more in reading books. To be tried.</p>

<h2 id="writing">Writing</h2>

<p>One of the annoyances I found out about this is to have a correction/revision for my writing, and to track my objectives.</p>

<p>For example, a process I’ve in mind is to have a list of <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">X</code> words daily, and I need to use them in a writing assignment of <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">100</code> words. The objective, similar to flashcards, is to hit each word <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">10</code> times at least.</p>

<p>A proxy for proper correction (to be investigated) is to use GPT model at the end to generate a correction for my writing, and use this as the ground truth for what I’ve truly practiced.</p>

<p>I am still trying different things. We will see how it goes.</p>

<h1 id="final-note">Final note</h1>

<p>This whole project was fun. I learned a lot of new things, and came to appreciate my own limitations on many other things (I will probably write about this separately).</p>

<ol>
  <li>It is a process design problem: Finding the right process to unlock the right functionality. I also found the hard way that my execution capacity was limited, unable to keep up with my design iterations (my experience and tech stack is geared more towards machine learning, research and backend, and not towards user-facing applications and interactions). This was a motive to improve and expand my design and technical skills.</li>
  <li>There is a deep value in having a progress bar and metrics to track my progress, even if they are noisy. Better still, it is nice to have the “one number” that summarize your progress. After that, you can have other numbers that shed light on different aspects of that progress.</li>
  <li>While perseverance is the key to progress forward, and I am already enjoying the mix of road building and exploration that I am doing: I think a key item is to <em>find a manageable objective</em>. Conversing fluently in French (my objective since forever) is unrealistic in the absence of full immersion, and immersion will not happen without a need or a stress, interior or exterior. But a limited immersion seems feasible (and personally interesting):
    <ol>
      <li>Reading: I love magazines (space, cars, tech), history, and eager to explore literature (Jules Verne in French? Let’s go!).</li>
      <li>Watching / Listening: I like documentaries in different subjects (<a href="https://www.arte.tv">ARTE</a> comes to mind).</li>
      <li>Writing small nuggets daily (~100 words or so), maybe focusing on using certain words, seems doable.</li>
    </ol>
  </li>
  <li>Conversation is still a challenge (particularly: hearing), but my hypothesis is: if I managed the other three, then when the opportunity comes to immerse, I will be better prepared.</li>
</ol>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="thinking" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Part 1 Part 2]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Debunking the Myths of the HBO Chernobyl series</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/investigation/2023/01/05/hbo-chernobyl-myth.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Debunking the Myths of the HBO Chernobyl series" /><published>2023-01-05T23:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2023-01-05T23:00:00+01:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/investigation/2023/01/05/hbo-chernobyl-myth</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/investigation/2023/01/05/hbo-chernobyl-myth.html"><![CDATA[<p>When I was a child, around 5-9 years old, I came across a story in the <em>Reader’s Digest</em> magazine (<em>El-Mokhtar</em> in its Arabic version) about the Chernobyl disaster.</p>

<p>It was about Anatoly Grishchenko, a Soviet helicopter pilot who had served in Chernobyl and, like many others, had developed cancer as a result. An incredible act of kindness and empathy from pilots in the United States saw them arrange for Grishchenko to come to the US to receive treatment, yet sadly he did not survive.<br />
(I could not find the original article, but here is <a href="https://www.latimes.com/archives/la-xpm-1990-07-04-mn-106-story.html">another article from that time</a>).</p>

<p>This story of humans from both sides of the aisle putting aside their differences to appreciate human life and sacrifice is something that I will never forget.</p>

<p>I was moved by the HBO series about Chernobyl. I watched it repeatedly, and had it on my to-do list to review the cassette tapes that Professor Valerie Legasov (the main figure in the series) recorded before his suicide in 1988. It was with a sense of excitement that I finally did so a few weeks ago.</p>

<p>However, what I found left me horrified. The tapes contradicted almost everything in the series, with the exception of the fact that the Chernobyl disaster did occur.</p>

<p>I cannot fathom what the motives behind this series could be. Is it simply to make a profit through entertainment? Or is it an intentional falsification of history? Or, worse still, is it an attempt to feed the narrative that nuclear energy is bad? This would be an incredibly dangerous message to spread, as nuclear energy is in fact much safer than coal or petrol. It has been given a bad reputation due to the nuclear arms race and the fear that it will lead to the end of the world.</p>

<p>You can find the transcripts of the tapes <a href="https://legasovtapetranslation.blogspot.com/">here</a>. The recordings are also available on YouTube.</p>

<h1 id="series-vs-tapes-point-by-point">Series VS tapes: point by point</h1>

<table><tbody><tr><td>HBO series claims</td><td>Legasov tapes</td></tr><tr><td>Legasov was portrayed as the primary scientist and the focal point of the entire Chernobyl operation.</td><td>He was one of many. He played a role, but he was not the central piece of the story.</td></tr><tr><td>The government response to the disaster was slow and inadequate.</td><td>Legasov commended the swiftness and efficiency of the government response at all levels. There were some minor issues, but overall, he deemed the response to be adequate.</td></tr><tr><td>There were not enough dosimeters with a wide enough range for the Chernobyl disaster. This led to large underestimations for the severity of the situation at the beginning.</td><td>Legasov did not mention this at all. It is unlikely he would have overlooked such an important detail if it had been true.</td></tr><tr><td>The series showed Legasov meeting Gorbachov in a committee meeting soon after he was called to help with the accident, and later in several other meetings.</td><td>This probably did not happen. Legasov never mentioned attending any central committee meetings or ever meeting Gorbachov. He only had a few phone calls with Gorbachov much later in the Chernobyl operations.</td></tr><tr><td>Legasov worked directly with Sherbina throughout the entire event.</td><td>It appears that there was one or two levels of hierarchy between them, and that the two did not work closely together.</td></tr><tr><td>Sherbina is portrayed as a stubborn bureaucratic person who was sent to Chernobyl because he was not important, implying that the government did not care much. Over the course of the events, he transforms into a good man who will do whatever is necessary to get the job done properly.</td><td>Legasov praised Sherbina's management and leadership from the beginning. He described him as highly competent and data-driven. He always sought the advice of experts for every decision from day one, and only carried out the experts' decisions.</td></tr><tr><td>The soviet government did not want to evacuate the town of Pripyat and that it only happened after the effects of the disaster were detected in Sweden and Germany.</td><td>Legasov indicated the opposite. He said that the decision to evacuate was made quickly, even though the levels of radiation in the town were not considered to be dangerous.<br />The main concern was to ensure an orderly evacuation, as seen in the Three Mile Island nuclear accident in the US, where the only fatalities were due to the lack of an orderly evacuation, not from the radiation. Legasov stressed that the main goal of the committee was to help the people.</td></tr><tr><td>The series implied that the communist committee in the city decided to "seal off" the city and that no one would leave.</td><td>Legasov made no mention of this. As stated previously, he was satisified with the speed, timing and quality of the evacuation.</td></tr><tr><td>The series claimed that the uranium fuel rods would melt through the reactor, contaminate the soil, and poison the Dnieper river.<br />In order to prevent this, the miners were brought in to dig under the reactor and install a heat exchange unit.</td><td>According to Legasov, the probability of this occurring was "extremely unlikely".<br />Despite this, the work was done due to the head of the committee's paranoia. Legasov believed that this work was unnecessary and excessive, but the only positive aspect was that it provided a sense of hope and motivation for the people to see men and machines "doing something."<br />Even two years after the Chernobyl disaster, Legasov stated that there was no possibility of this scenario occurring.</td></tr><tr><td>There were political motives for avoiding decisions such as the evacuation of Pripyat and increasing the evacuation zone, as well as obtaining the necessary equipment.</td><td>Legasov insisted that the committee's work was data-driven, professional, and calm. When the right decision was unknown, it was based on trial and error.</td></tr><tr><td>The government made an effort to conceal everything regarding the accident and what was happening.</td><td>Legasov stated that this was not the case, and that information was not provided at the time because it didn't exist. The situation was very confusing, and information was scarce, coming from multiple conflicting sources and estimates, making it difficult to collect, filter, and access the correct information.</td></tr><tr><td>The water tanks in the reactor were full, and the uranium fuel rods were at risk of melting through the water tanks, potentially releasing a force equivalent to a multi-megaton nuclear device and devastating much of Europe with radiation.</td><td>The water tanks were full, but there was no risk of such an explosion. The main concern was that the evaporated water would carry radioactive materials away from the reactor, making the situation more difficult to contain.</td></tr><tr><td>The KGB was following him, arresting some of the scientists involved in investigating the causes of the disaster, and doing whatever it can to prevent the other reactors from being fixed.<br />They punished Legasov, placing him under house arrest for his testimony against the state, which ultimately led to his decision to commit suicide.</td><td>Legasov praised the KGB for their professionalism, organization, and help with communications and logistics. No other actions were mentioned. Additionally, there is no evidence that Legasov was arrested by the KGB (even according to Wikipedia).<br /></td></tr><tr><td>Legasov committed suicide in order to send a message about the lies of the Soviet state.</td><td>According to Wikipedia, Legasov attempted suicide multiple times due to worsening health and increasing confrontation with his colleagues and academics, which deepened his depression.</td></tr><tr><td>When Legasov arrived at Chernobyl, the core of the reactor was active, releasing radiation equivalent to many Hiroshima bombs every hour.</td><td>The core of the reactor was not active. The spread of radiation to great distances was due to dry dust and contaminated vehicles being dispersed to various areas. This was a stressful challenge for the decontamination efforts to handle, but it was not as catastrophic as many "Hiroshima bombs every hour".</td></tr><tr><td>The series emphasized the use of robots, such as the lunar rover and the German "Joker," to remove radioactive material.</td><td>Legasov debunked the successful use of robots for this purpose, noting that they were fragile, ill-equipped to handle obstacles, and inadequate for the job. Radio-controlled bulldozers and shielded vehicles were far more effective.</td></tr><tr><td>The German "Joker" robot became inoperable because government officials lowered the radiation requirements when they ordered it, in order to conceal the magnitude of the Chernobyl disaster.</td><td>Legasov debunked this story, describing it as a myth. While the robot was shielded against radiation, it was not designed to handle obstacles and debris. Hot graphite particles melted inside the bottom of the robot, compromising the radiation shield and exposing the control circuits to radiation, which fried the robot circuits.</td></tr></tbody></table>

<p>Long story short, there were a lot of rumors and myths spread in the media and the press at the time. It was unfortunate, but this can happen during such disasters, where clear information and assessment of the situation are absent, or due to misaligned motives (Remember that the press is made of…people, and people could aspire for fame and glory and personal fortunes, and these come from excitement and hype. Not all news fit this criteria, so, you might cherry-pick what to report, or spice some of the news).<br />
However, 30 years later, the series basically gave a rebirth to these rumors, and set aside any other information. It is more appealing this way, right?</p>

<h1 id="additional-information-from-the-tapes">Additional information from the tapes</h1>

<p>Beside the differences, Legasov added a lot of interesting details, and his point of view on things. I highly recommend you listen to the tapes or read the transcripts. Beautiful observations and thinking.<br />
I will mention some of those details here, because they are relevant to the comprehending why the Chernobyl disaster happened in the first place, and I believe they are relevant nowadays as well.</p>

<ol>
  <li>
    <p>Absence of a communications group in the committee: Legasov proposed to the committee to create a Communications Group to ensure proper communication and the release of accurate information, particularly in the form of brochures to inform the public about how to respond to the situation. However, the committee decided that this was not a priority, so the idea was put aside. This ultimately caused an increase in miscommunication and the spread of rumors.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>Criticism for the press: Legasov heavily criticized the press, noting that they were not interested in the true story of what happened, or providing the audience with the necessary context. Instead, they sought out the most sensationalistic stories and headlines. He also pointed out that very few experts were giving statements, which only served to fuel rumors and misinformation. Furthermore, some misguided projects and procedures were created as a result of what was written in the press, further complicating the important work.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>Criticism for the academic society: Legasov criticized severely the academic society for its hostility towards new ideas, exclusion of those who disagree with the mainstream, and its disconnection from reality. There is a lack of risk-taking mentality, with the expectation that people should just do the same as before or risk being ostracized.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>Criticism for the nuclear energy industry in the USSR: The nuclear energy industry in the USSR faced criticism due to the lack of an industry in place. To quickly increase its nuclear energy capacity, research devices were hastily adapted for industrial use, resulting in complex and potentially hazardous machinery, such as the RBMK reactor of Chernobyl, that didn’t follow industry standards such as safety, ease of use, and quality. These devices were suitable for smaller scale operations managed by highly trained professionals, however, large scale industrial usage without such professionals could lead to catastrophic outcomes.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>Nuclear energy is the future: Legasov argues that nuclear energy is far cleaner and cheaper than coal, and produces less radioactive pollution than coal and oil. Coal contains naturally-occurring radioactive material, which is released into the air when it is burned, along with other pollutants. Additionally, the cost of extracting and transporting coal is higher than that of uranium. Nuclear power plants may be more expensive initially, but over time they are far cheaper. I highly recommend you to watch a <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=cbeJIwF1pVY">this video</a> to better understand the economics of nuclear energy.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>The civil defense: He praised the organization of the various working groups, but criticized the civil defense as disorganized and unruly.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>Poor quality of training and readiness for the staff operating the reactor.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>Measuring performance by the increase in the number of personal and material, not the quality: In the USSR, there was an increasing focus on quantity rather than quality when measuring performance. This was reflected in the construction of more buildings, the production of more materials, and the hiring of more people. The various departments grew in size, but there was no corresponding growth in quality or other key metrics.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>Competent engineers, but not critical of the devices and tools they are using: Even though there were highly skilled engineers and qualified personnel, they were only proficient in using the tools and devices without questioning them. As a result, many inadequate tools and devices were accepted without any critical evaluation due to the lack of questioning and critical thinking.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>There were a lot of talks about the need for improvements in conferences and parties, but no action.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>Scientific leadership was reduced to providing technical advice, rather than making policy decisions. This shift in the USSR saw bureaucrats and engineers taking the reins, leading to a lack of comprehension for the consequences of their decisions due to a limited understanding of the scientific phenomena they were trying to control.</p>
  </li>
  <li>Cultural and political factors:
    <ul>
      <li>
        <p>The USSR lacked a safety culture, and similar issues could be found in other industries.</p>
      </li>
      <li>
        <p>Isolation from the rest of the world meant that the USSR did not benefit from the experience of other countries. This was evident in the RBMK reactor, which was considered subpar in all aspects, even economically, as it was developed domestically and disregarded the common experience of other countries.</p>
      </li>
      <li>
        <p>The complex relationship between science and engineering, risk and conservatism, dynamism and rigidity was destroyed by bureaucracy and wrong incentives for the wrong metrics over many years.</p>
      </li>
    </ul>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>Shared/distributed ownership with too many people, and overlapping responsibilities: Having too many people with shared/distributed ownership and overlapping responsibilities led to a lack of responsibility, accountability, and confusion due to the absence of separation of concerns, resulting in a decrease in quality. No one was held accountable, and everyone was absolved of guilt. Legasov advocated for single owners and clear responsibilities.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>Bad operational management in the nuclear industry: Poor operational management in the nuclear industry caused a lack of clarity in processes, working procedures, training, and operational standards. Documentation was inadequate, and there was no follow-up on the implementation of commands. Complex procedures were not practiced prior to their execution.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>The “parachute specialists” phenomena: Legasov noted that many specialists, who lacked scientific or engineering backgrounds, suddenly appeared. They spoke, conversed, made demands, and expressed requirements that were not realistic. They had no understanding of the Soviet Union’s machine industry and what it was capable of producing. This led to a distorted and incoherent picture.</p>
  </li>
  <li>Legasov summarized his advice on how to approach the development of nuclear - or any other safety critical - devices in three points as such:
    <ul>
      <li>
        <p>Enhance the safety of the device by designing it to be safe from the beginning, and incorporating multiple independent emergency mechanisms.</p>
      </li>
      <li>
        <p>Increase the reliability and usability of the device by making it as simple as possible to operate and understand, and by rigorously testing it to ensure it can withstand extreme conditions.</p>
      </li>
      <li>
        <p>Prepare for accidents by containing the damage, training staff, and continuously revising, criticizing, and improving procedures.</p>
      </li>
    </ul>
  </li>
</ol>

<h1 id="articles-criticizing-the-series">Articles criticizing the series</h1>

<p>I did some search on this before I started. There are multiple articles that are published on “What is wrong with the HBO Chernobyl series”, however, they tackle one of two axes:</p>

<ol>
  <li>
    <p>Either cultural issues: the way Legasov spoke during the trial in a heroic manner (spelling the truth out load) - resignation seems to be the defining condition of the Soviet life -, or how Sherbina threaten to get Legasov shot at the beginning (remember the days of Stalin, which was no longer the case at the point of time).</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>Or the consequences of Chernobyl: which is a whole topic of its own, that will be the subject of my second article (if I get myself to write it). Long story short, the health consequences of the Chernobyl has been massively inflated by either the series, or the media in general.</p>
  </li>
</ol>

<p>Strangely enough, no one addressed the issue of the tapes before - to the best of my knowledge - (if you know of a published work where this was mentioned, please correct me).</p>

<h1 id="final-thoughts">Final thoughts</h1>

<p>Does any of this sound familiar in today’s world? It’s clear that Legasov and others saw it coming long before Chernobyl; it was only a matter of time before it happened.</p>

<p>I’m inclined to agree with him on all these points; not just because of what he said, but because we’re still living through it now.</p>

<p>….</p>

<p>After much thinking and a struggle to find the words, I’ve come to the conclusion that lying for personal reasons is something I’m okay with. Sure, it’s my own choice and I’m the one who will bear the consequences.</p>

<p>But when it comes to public awareness, consciousness and accountability, deception is something that makes me feel sick to my stomach. The odd thing is, we all seem to know that we’re being deceived and yet we’re still okay with it.</p>

<p>One of my friends said to me, “What’s the problem if it’s future generations that will have to bear the brunt of it?” I can’t comprehend it.</p>

<p>There’s an argument that technology is to blame for the mass brainwashing of people, but this has been happening for centuries. I can sense a strange distortion in society, an impending sense of doom, and it’s hard to put into words. It’s like we’ve chosen to ignore the truth in favor of a good story or a good feeling. We’ve defined a good life as one filled with positive emotions, but it’s almost like we’re choosing to be sedated because reality is too uncomfortable.</p>

<p>Chernobyl is a perfect example of a situation that forced people to face reality, to some degree, but there are so many other issues that have gone unnoticed, like data privacy, the monetary system, the spread of bullshit jobs and the handling of the COVID-19 pandemic.</p>

<p>I’m becoming more and more convinced that the only way to live peacefully is to isolate myself from society and live quietly and insignificantly.</p>

<h1 id="acknowledgement">Acknowledgement</h1>

<p>Thanks a lot for those who took the time to review this work and give me feedback on it: Anya and her mom, Makia, and my young sister Zynab.</p>

<p>And many thanks for those who took the time to advise me on different issues about this work: Sawsen, Dan, Frederic and Gael.</p>

<h1 id="references">References</h1>

<ol>
  <li>
    <p>Valery Legasov tapes - transcripts in English: <a href="https://legasovtapetranslation.blogspot.com/">https://legasovtapetranslation.blogspot.com/</a></p>
  </li>
  <li>Wikipedia on Valery Legasov: <a href="https://en.m.wikipedia.org/wiki/Valery_Legasov">https://en.m.wikipedia.org/wiki/Valery_Legasov</a>
    <ul>
      <li>Interesting since it describes the circumstances of his suicide.</li>
    </ul>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>Anatoly Grishchenko Story: <a href="https://www.latimes.com/archives/la-xpm-1990-07-04-mn-106-story.html">https://www.latimes.com/archives/la-xpm-1990-07-04-mn-106-story.html</a></p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>The economics of nuclear power: <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=cbeJIwF1pVY">https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=cbeJIwF1pVY</a></p>
  </li>
  <li>Articles criticizing the HBO Chernobyl series
    <ul>
      <li>Cultural reasons
        <ul>
          <li><a href="https://www.newyorker.com/news/our-columnists/what-hbos-chernobyl-got-right-and-what-it-got-terribly-wrong">https://www.newyorker.com/news/our-columnists/what-hbos-chernobyl-got-right-and-what-it-got-terribly-wrong</a></li>
        </ul>
      </li>
      <li>The inflation of Chernobyl consequences
        <ul>
          <li>
            <p><a href="https://www.forbes.com/sites/jamesconca/2019/06/27/how-hbo-got-it-wrong-on-chernobyl/">https://www.forbes.com/sites/jamesconca/2019/06/27/how-hbo-got-it-wrong-on-chernobyl/</a></p>
          </li>
          <li>
            <p><a href="https://www.forbes.com/sites/michaelshellenberger/2019/06/06/why-hbos-chernobyl-gets-nuclear-so-wrong/">https://www.forbes.com/sites/michaelshellenberger/2019/06/06/why-hbos-chernobyl-gets-nuclear-so-wrong/</a></p>
          </li>
        </ul>
      </li>
    </ul>
  </li>
  <li>Craig Mazin (the creator of the HBO Chernobyl series) interview, claiming that he stuck to the details and the truth: <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=yY0r1Ln6tkM">https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=yY0r1Ln6tkM</a>
    <ul>
      <li>Unbelievable really, given that there is not a single point I found so far in the series that matches reality (other than that Chernobyl happened).</li>
    </ul>
  </li>
  <li>Consequences of Chernobyl: Very interesting read summarizing the consequences of Chernobyl, after 20 years of studies and observation by the different UN agencies and independent research
    <ul>
      <li>
        <p>Chernobyl Forum (report): <a href="https://www.iaea.org/sites/default/files/chernobyl.pdf">https://www.iaea.org/sites/default/files/chernobyl.pdf</a></p>
      </li>
      <li>
        <p>Chernobyl: Catastrophe and consequences (book): https://link.springer.com/book/10.1007/3-540-28079-0</p>
      </li>
    </ul>
  </li>
</ol>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="investigation" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[When I was a child, around 5-9 years old, I came across a story in the Reader’s Digest magazine (El-Mokhtar in its Arabic version) about the Chernobyl disaster.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">A view on France - Part 2</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/data-science/machine-learning/nlp/2022/08/19/french-journey-part-2.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="A view on France - Part 2" /><published>2022-08-19T00:00:00+02:00</published><updated>2022-08-19T00:00:00+02:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/data-science/machine-learning/nlp/2022/08/19/french-journey-part-2</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/data-science/machine-learning/nlp/2022/08/19/french-journey-part-2.html"><![CDATA[<p>Following on my journey to explore the French language (check <a href="https://osm3000.wordpress.com/2022/02/16/a-view-on-france-part-1/">part 1</a>), in this part I wanted to better understand how to many articles do I need to read randomly from LeMonde in order to reach my learning objectives, and if there is a way to guide this process (instead of just random articles). The code for the <a href="https://github.com/osm3000/Language-Analysis/blob/dirty_experiment/heavy_exp.py">simulation is here</a>, the analysis is <a href="https://github.com/osm3000/Language-Analysis/blob/dirty_experiment/number_of_articles_to_master_french.ipynb">available here</a>.</p>

<h1 id="boring-background">Boring background</h1>

<p>A question that always fascinated me to quantify the learning of a new language.</p>

<ol>
  <li>How to represent the ‘learning process’ in an objective way?</li>
  <li>How much effort is required to reach this objective?</li>
  <li>Can I optimize my efforts in order to achieve higher efficiency?</li>
</ol>

<p>Beside curiosity, the motivation from this analysis is pave the way building a learning system for myself, that can monitor my training and progress, and optimize my learning trajectory.</p>

<p>Of course, it can be argued that maybe it is better to spend the time in actually learning French than analyzing it. There are two points here:</p>

<ol>
  <li>Despite huge efforts to learn French (and to some extent I can speak and comprehend what people are saying at the moment), the gains have been low. Believe it or not, in academia and a lot of tech companies nowadays, there is no natural need/urgency to speak French! And everyone speaks English.</li>
  <li>I like to understand how things work from first principles point of view.</li>
  <li>I realize more and more that, even in English, my vocabulary is becoming more and more limited. Being in France, speaking English with people from many nationalities, you end up mastering what’s called “international English” and build a habit for using simpler, limited set of vocabulary.</li>
</ol>

<p>Vocabulary are the building blocks for thinking. It represents the ability to abstract concepts and ideas, thus, it allows me to remove the clutter, and see connections and relations that were not obvious before.<br />
Thus, aside from French, I would like to use such a system for English as well, to maintain or expand or my skills.</p>

<p>While I am focusing on <em>reading articles from LeMonde</em> as the only way to learn, which is unrealistic for sure, it is a start. One can imagine combining this data from other streams of data (which I will do), like Twitter, Reddit, Podcast/Video transcripts, ….etc.</p>

<p>Plus, most importantly, I fucking love numbers :D</p>

<h1 id="assumptions">Assumptions</h1>

<p>It is important to consider the simplifications and assumptions made here in this analysis</p>

<ol>
  <li>I am assuming that learning French = learning 80% of the most common French vocabulary. This is ~2600 words. To understand how I got those words, check <a href="https://osm3000.wordpress.com/2022/02/16/a-view-on-france-part-1/">part 1</a>.
    <ol>
      <li>The previous analysis was done on a small sample of articles, mostly from the recent couple of years. I have redone this calculation from scratch for the 1 million LeMonde articles used in this new analysis, and concluded that 80% of the French language is ~3500 words.</li>
    </ol>
  </li>
  <li>“Learning those words” translates to: seeing each word at least 10 times.</li>
  <li>Every 100 articles, I model “memory loss”: for each word of the target vocabulary that I didn’t see in the last 100 articles, I will reduce its score by 1 point (If you don’t practice, you will forget).</li>
  <li>While it is simplified to translate learning French to learning 80% of the words, and it is focused only on the “reading” part, and it might be criticized as language is more than just words, I would argue that it can be an <em>okay</em> proxy:
    <ol>
      <li>You are not learning the words in isolation here, that is the beauty of learning by reading articles.</li>
      <li>The more you articles, the more likely that you will see different combinations and uses of those words.</li>
      <li>The definite and ultimate test here is a random-controlled experiment: try on two groups of people, a control group (using the naive approach) and the optimized one. Which one perform better? However, it is unlikely I would be able to perform such an experiment. Maybe my analysis will encourage someone to do so :)</li>
    </ol>
  </li>
</ol>

<h1 id="how-does-the-optimization-works">How does the optimization works?</h1>

<p>It is a simple mix of random + greedy optimization. To select the next article to read:</p>

<ol>
  <li>Sample 100 articles from the whole dataset.</li>
  <li>Select the one of them article that maximizes the learning objective.</li>
</ol>

<h1 id="results-of-different-approaches-to-learning">Results of different approaches to learning</h1>

<p>One can imagine that the good thing to do is to practice everyday (which is in general a good thing to do). Normally, you will focus on a couple of topics that interests you, read an article from here or there. Basically, this mounts to picking up random articles (to some extent).</p>

<p>This is how your performance will look like this:</p>

<p><a href="https://osm3000.files.wordpress.com/2022/06/something_2-2.png"><img src="https://osm3000.files.wordpress.com/2022/06/something_2-2.png?w=1024" alt="" /></a></p>

<p>Progress in achieving the objective if you pick up articles at random (in blue) vs using an optimized/curated set of articles (in orange)</p>

<p>Here you see the traditional wisdom of diminishing returns (or in some avenue that 80-20 rule), which is expected. You progress fast at the</p>

<p>It is very difficult to hit the objective in this scenario of 100%.</p>

<p>However, with optimized articles, we can see that it you can hit your objective in less than 400 articles. The difference is massive!</p>

<h1 id="years-distributions-for-both-strategies"><em>Years</em> distributions for both strategies</h1>

<ul>
  <li>
    <p><img src="https://osm3000.files.wordpress.com/2022/08/random_years_distribution.png?w=1024" alt="" /></p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p><img src="https://osm3000.files.wordpress.com/2022/08/optimized_years_distribution.png?w=1024" alt="" /></p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p><img src="https://osm3000.files.wordpress.com/2022/08/years_absolute_difference-1.png?w=1024" alt="" /></p>

    <p>This is the frequency of years for optimized strategy - random strategy</p>
  </li>
</ul>

<p>Is this difference statistically significant? YES! And visually clear too! For years 2000, 2001, 2002, 2003, 2004, 2005, 2006, 2007, 2008, 2009, 2010, 2011, 2012, 2013, 2014, 2015, 2016, 2017, 2018, 2019, 2020, 2021, 2022. This is basically all the visually different years that you see in the previous graphs.</p>

<p>There is also a difference between both strategies in focusing on different years. We see the years from 2014 until now having increasing importance for the optimized strategy, in comparison with the random strategy.</p>

<h1 id="topics-distributions-for-both-strategies"><em>Topics</em> distributions for both strategies</h1>

<p>I have also looked the category of topics from which these articles come from. This one wasn’t clear how to analyze to how look at.</p>

<p>I will spare you the line the thinking and all the annoyances that came with it. But let’s say the final outcome is this specific question: given the two strategies, is there a difference between the frequency of the topics in both cases?</p>

<p>If we consider the frequency only and consider the top 25 topics only (from each strategy, there is around 295 topics generated), we can see that there is a statistical difference almost in every topic. Which is COOL! until you see what that looks like exactly.</p>

<p><a href="https://osm3000.files.wordpress.com/2022/06/top_25_topics_means-1.png"><img src="https://osm3000.files.wordpress.com/2022/06/top_25_topics_means-1.png?w=1024" alt="" /></a></p>

<p>The percentage of appearance (on the X axis) for difference topics in both strategies. Although you can see some differences, it is hard for me to say that these are fundamentally different.</p>

<p>It is hard to make such conclusion of significance difference visually, unlike in the case of the years. The differences increase when the topics are less frequent, but that is not a surprise. From one side, maybe a bigger sample is needed to get a good estimation about the actual distribution of the topics in the data, and from the other side, the optimization might have been working too hard to squeeze any drop of performance from anywhere.</p>

<p>So, instead of frequencies, I looked at the ranking of 25 most important topics in both strategies. Now we can start to more clearer differences.</p>

<p><a href="https://osm3000.files.wordpress.com/2022/06/top_25_topics_ranking-2.png"><img src="https://osm3000.files.wordpress.com/2022/06/top_25_topics_ranking-2.png?w=1024" alt="" /></a></p>

<p>Looking at the ranking of the topic instead of the frequency gives a different perspective. High ranking means high frequency. Some differences exist for the top topics. But when you go to the lower topics, the differences become much clearer.</p>

<p>For the first 14 topics, the differences are not that much, but for the next 11 topics, we can see clear differences. For example, there is almost 10 points difference in the ranking ‘sciences’ between both strategies.</p>

<h1 id="closing-remarks">Closing remarks</h1>

<p>I hope I have given an indication to support the case for optimized strategy <em>vs</em> a naive one.</p>

<p>On the surprising part for me: I didn’t expect that some years are more important than other years! I didn’t it for the Lolz mainly, but that was a cool outcome.</p>

<p>I am not surprised that there is a difference in the topics, but the dimensions of this difference (like in the topic ‘sciences’ for example) are surprising for me.</p>

<h1 id="things-to-consider-for-later">Things to consider for later</h1>

<p>What I like about a project is when it breeds new projects and ideas, and new questions to address :)</p>

<ol>
  <li>Some parts of this analysis were very time consuming from the computer, and multiple activities were using a fraction of the computer power, but they were blocking activities. This is really annoying. Fast iterations are key in order to explore new ideas. There are few directions I am considering from this point:
    <ol>
      <li>I need to profile each piece of code that I wrote: in general, this is a good practice. There can be ways to increase the efficiency from one, or a need to rethink about the problem in a different way that is more efficient. As a good rule of thumb, there is usually a better way.</li>
      <li>Use statistical samples instead of doing exhaustive search: I think this is the direction I am more interested in, and closer to my experience. The main challenge for me in this project is to move from the ‘exhaustive’ mindset to a statistical mindset. I definitely underestimated the time needs in this project.</li>
      <li>Use different framework: I intend to explore Spark for NLP at one point. I don’t yet what it can bring to this type of analysis. To be seen.</li>
      <li>Invest more in pre-processing: for example, extract a bag of words for each article in advance, and store it in the database. That will make it easy to perform some aspects of this analysis. However, this does have its drawbacks.
        <ol>
          <li>In this kind of exploratory projects, it is hard to know what do I want in advance. The questions evolve with time.</li>
          <li>The hard disk consumption is high (~30 Gb already for the current data). Adding a lot of metadata just because I can will add extra storage usage, which is not wise at the moment.</li>
        </ol>
      </li>
      <li>Moving the work to a bigger machine: happening soon.</li>
      <li>More emphasis on using the database: yes, I still have the tendency to use ‘.json’ files over proper use of the database. In the case of NLP tasks like this, I am not sure what a scalable workflow looks like.</li>
    </ol>
  </li>
  <li>I am considering building a small web app, in order to test this. I want to try this on myself first, and make it available for other who would like to try as well. Would I actually improve my French? Will I, at the very least, master 80% of the words? (I know how to form the sentences, the vocabulary for me is a critical point).</li>
  <li>Why some years are more vocabulary-rich than others? For the years, after discussing with a couple of friends, it might be due to certain unique events that happened at those years. For example, 2001-2002 was the terrorism events, with new words suddenly becoming more dominant. A similar story can be said about 2020-2021, with the lovely era of covid. I will think about a way to analyze this.</li>
  <li>In my analysis, I considered both the years and the topics separately. It will be interesting to consider both of them together.</li>
  <li>Adding more ‘natural’ sources of data: like twitter/reddit/movies &amp; TV-series subtitles. After all, the language LeMonde doesn’t necessarily represent what the language of the normal French person.</li>
</ol>

<p>If you have some suggestion, comment or a feedback, I would love to know and discuss it :)</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="data-science" /><category term="machine-learning" /><category term="nlp" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Following on my journey to explore the French language (check part 1), in this part I wanted to better understand how to many articles do I need to read randomly from LeMonde in order to reach my learning objectives, and if there is a way to guide this process (instead of just random articles). The code for the simulation is here, the analysis is available here.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Startup funding status (France and UK)</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/startups/funding/2022/07/07/startup-funding-status.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Startup funding status (France and UK)" /><published>2022-07-07T00:00:00+02:00</published><updated>2022-07-07T00:00:00+02:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/startups/funding/2022/07/07/startup-funding-status</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/startups/funding/2022/07/07/startup-funding-status.html"><![CDATA[<p>I was curious recently about what is happening in the startup world, given the grim expectations for the economy.</p>

<p><strong>The question is simple: how the startup funding is affected by the recent expectations in the economy?</strong></p>

<p>To answer this question, I used the data from Crunchbase to get the information about the following types of funding: pre-seed, seed, series-a, series-b and grants, for both France and UK. I got the data for the period from 01/01/2020 to 30/06/2022 (to give a context).</p>

<p>The word on the street is that pre-seed and seed are fine (they are long term investments, and investors need to keep their money working), and that funding will tighten up for later investment stages.</p>

<p>One analysis I was referred to <a href="https://jordanpascasio.substack.com/p/2022-q1?s=r">this analysis for the US startup world</a>. In a nutshell, what it concludes is that seed rounds will not be affected (it might increase), but later stages of funding will be affected. The idea is that other markets (in Europe) will follow the same. Unfortunately, getting the data for the US is more difficult (I am only a starter package from Crunchbase), thus I could verify the claims in the article.</p>

<h1 id="highlights">Highlights:</h1>

<ol>
  <li>The number of funding rounds for Pre-Seed is steadily declining for the last 3 quarters.</li>
  <li>The amount of money raised in Pre-Seed and seed didn’t decrease accordingly, suggesting it is becoming more concentrated (more money per round).</li>
  <li>The number of seed rounds is declining sharply in the last 1-2 quarters, same for the amount of money for this stage.</li>
  <li>While there is a change in the numbers for Series-A and Series-B in the last quarter, there are no clear patterns yet.</li>
</ol>

<h1 id="-view-1-number-of-funding-rounds"># View 1: Number of funding rounds</h1>

<p>One thing the original article doesn’t mention is the number of rounds. They discuss it only from the perspective of total capital invested. So it is hard to know if more capital is allocated to fewer startups.</p>

<p>Looking at the number of funding rounds, you can see interesting trends. I will look at it per quarter (after too many views, this one is much less noisy and more clearer than the others).</p>

<ul>
  <li>
    <p><img src="https://osm3000.files.wordpress.com/2022/07/uk-performance-quarter.png?w=1024" alt="" /></p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p><img src="https://osm3000.files.wordpress.com/2022/07/france-performance-quarter.png?w=1024" alt="" /></p>

    <p>Looking at the number of rounds for each type of investment per quarter.</p>
  </li>
</ul>

<p>Pre-Seed: we can see that both UK and France are experiencing decline in the number of rounds of the last 3 quarter already, beyond the lowest levels since Q1-2020.</p>

<p>Seed:</p>

<ul>
  <li>UK: it is already declining in the last 2 quarters. Last quarter in particular is pretty steep.</li>
  <li>France: It declines very steeply in the last quarter.</li>
</ul>

<p>Series-A:</p>

<ul>
  <li>UK: It went down in Q2-2022, but there is no clear pattern yet.</li>
  <li>France: After a huge jump in Q1-2022 (Can someone explain this to me?), it is going down in Q2-2022. There is no clear pattern yet.</li>
</ul>

<p>Series-B:</p>

<ul>
  <li>UK: It went down in Q2-2022, but there is no clear pattern yet.</li>
  <li>France: it seems to hold steady for many quarters already, and in Q2-2022, it even increased!</li>
</ul>

<p>Grants: for both UK and France, the number of grants have declined in last quarter, but compared to previous patterns, nothing is out of the ordinary yet.</p>

<p><em>One interesting thing to note is the slope of decline: the earlier the funding stage, the faster the decline (larger slope).</em></p>

<h1 id="-view-2-money-raised"># View 2: Money raised</h1>

<p>The original article focused only on the money raised. Thus, I wanted to explore this particular point.</p>

<p><strong>Warning</strong>: some reported investment rounds on Crunchbase don’t declare the amount of money raised. For UK: 4550 declared vs 1242 not declared, and for France, I have 1227 declared vs 261 not declared. In order to address this problem, I statistically filled the gaps (sample a value from a multi-nomial distribution fitted on the same investment stage for the same year and quarter).</p>

<ul>
  <li>
    <p><img src="https://osm3000.files.wordpress.com/2022/07/uk-money_raised-quarter-2.png?w=1024" alt="" /></p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p><img src="https://osm3000.files.wordpress.com/2022/07/france-money_raised-quarter-2.png?w=1024" alt="" /></p>
  </li>
</ul>

<p>Pre-Seed: it is hard to determine a pattern here.</p>

<p>Seed:</p>

<ul>
  <li>UK: It is steadily decreasing in the last two quarters.</li>
  <li>France: it decrease a lot in the in the last quarter. Yet, no clear pattern.</li>
</ul>

<p>Series-A: for both UK and France, I can’t see a pattern here.</p>

<p>Series-B:</p>

<ul>
  <li>UK: last quarter was unprecedentedly low, with a very steep decline.</li>
  <li>France: it went up! Not sure how to explain that.</li>
</ul>

<p>Grants: no clear pattern to observe both countries.</p>

<p>This is in general strange. I was expecting the pattern for the amount of money raised to follow the number of funding rounds.</p>

<h1 id="view-3-amount-of-money-raised-vs-number-of-funding-rounds">View 3: Amount of money raised VS number of funding rounds</h1>

<p>Following view 2, I wanted to see more what is the relationship between both the total amount of money raised, and the number of funding rounds.</p>

<p>This is the correlation table here:</p>

<p><a href="https://osm3000.files.wordpress.com/2022/07/screenshot-2022-07-09-at-13.39.35.png"><img src="https://osm3000.files.wordpress.com/2022/07/screenshot-2022-07-09-at-13.39.35.png?w=500" alt="" /></a></p>

<p>Pearson correlation between the total amount of money raised and the number of funding rounds for each funding stage, in UK and France.<br />
Pearson correlation coefficient is between -1 (inverse linear relationship) to +1 (positive relationship). The closer to zero, the less the relationship is.</p>

<p>While Grants, Seed (to some extent), Series-A and B are expected (the more the money, the more the funding rounds, and vise versa), Pre-Seed is interesting.</p>

<ol>
  <li>It is weakly correlated in France. This explains the weird phenomena: The total money raised didn’t decrease, while the number of rounds decreased. The money is becoming more concentrated on some directions.</li>
  <li>It is negatively correlated in UK! The more money existing in the market, the fewer the number of funding rounds. But the less money existing in the market, the more the number of funding rounds it goes to!</li>
</ol>

<h1 id="things-to-consider">Things to consider</h1>

<ol>
  <li>I am not 100% sure if the data on Crunchbase is really up to date in France. I checked a couple of pre-seed startups that I know of in France, and I couldn’t find relevant information about them. It might be complete enough to capture the general picture though (if you have insights about this, or you know other sources of raw data, please let me know).</li>
  <li>I need to analyze if there is a time lag between France and UK. Just for fun!</li>
</ol>

<p>I would deeply appreciate if you can share opinions or different ways of reading this data, or different sources of data.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="startups" /><category term="funding" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[I was curious recently about what is happening in the startup world, given the grim expectations for the economy.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Building my own tablet</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/electronics/engineering/thinking/2022/04/13/buidling-tablet.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Building my own tablet" /><published>2022-04-13T00:00:00+02:00</published><updated>2022-04-13T00:00:00+02:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/electronics/engineering/thinking/2022/04/13/buidling-tablet</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/electronics/engineering/thinking/2022/04/13/buidling-tablet.html"><![CDATA[<p>Over the last couple of years, I came to the conclusion that I need to have a higher degree of control over my environment:</p>

<ul>
  <li>I need to be able to optimize the items in a way that is suitable for my own usage</li>
  <li>I want to be able to repair my stuff when they break, or upgrade the necessary components only (I am deeply affected by the <em>right to repair</em> movement).
    <ul>
      <li>I would highly recommend watching this <a href="https://www.youtube.com/playlist?list=PLTlJK3kwZIbSKCvNBA53Mdx4nST5TZs4Q">mini-series</a> for real-life examples and implications .</li>
    </ul>
  </li>
  <li>When there is a problem/new need, I want to make a solution to address it, in the way that best fits me</li>
</ul>

<p>This applies to the software that I am using and to physical items in the room/office.</p>

<p>I’ve been thinking a lot about privacy and security (for the electronic tools). Even though we know about that these devices (phones in particular) collects huge amount of data through their sensors about me, it seems I am powerless to do anything about it. So, at the moment, I am in the mindset of: let’s stop it at the source.</p>

<p>One of these project is to make my own tablet/lightweight laptop. A big motivation is that I need an e-reader. My book situation at the moment is super critical. I wasn’t really satisfied was any e-reader I found in the market.</p>

<p>I came to realize during this project that the inability of making my things/the direct acceptance of what is already out there, have destroyed a lot my taste and even the awareness of what I really like and what I don’t like. Designing and building things, that I will have to use, led to the emergence of these questions, and to many iterations to understand what I like and I don’t like. It is not just an engineering/technical processes, it is a journey inside who I am. It’s a process.</p>

<p>I am also realizing that pure consumerism life has negative psychological impact on me. It’s like my soul is getting fat. I’ve to pray that what I need exists on Amazon, and even with that, I no longer knew what I need. I go to get something, ends up with something else irrelevant to the original problem, and the cycle continues.</p>

<p>It feels that, even though somehow the options has increased over the year (you have so many phones from many manufactures available), the actual meaningful choices decreased. It seems that the choices based on the price range increase, but not based on the design choices (all the phones look exactly the same for example! but you will find a phone suitable for each budget).</p>

<h1 id="specifications">Specifications</h1>

<p>At the beginning, what I wanted is:</p>

<ul>
  <li>A tablet for reading: 10-inch touch screen of course!</li>
  <li>Mobile enough: maybe not the same as a commercial tablet, but must be easy to move and get it up and running in no time.</li>
  <li>Long battery life</li>
  <li>60 GB of storage, 4-8 Gb of RAM.</li>
  <li>Fixable and upgradable: if something breaks, I should be able to fix it/replace the broken parts. I identify the points of fix/upgrade/replace to be:
    <ul>
      <li>The computing unit</li>
      <li>The memory (SDcard): replace if there is a problem, or get a larger one.</li>
      <li>The screen</li>
      <li>The battery: get a larger/smaller/different battery.</li>
      <li>The enclosure/support/mounts</li>
    </ul>
  </li>
</ul>

<h1 id="hardware-used">Hardware used</h1>

<ul>
  <li>Computing: I hesitated between a <em><a href="https://www.raspberrypi.com/products/raspberry-pi-4-model-b/">Raspberry Pi 4 B+</a></em> (powerful, large, many peripherals, but more power hungry) or <em>Raspberry Pi Zero</em> (less powerful, more compact, less peripherals, power efficient). I decided to go for the <em>Pi 4</em>, since it gave me a big room to maneuver in this project. Maybe in a later iteration I will choose something different.</li>
  <li>Screen: in the absence of better judgement, I just choose a screen from Amazon, that has mounts in the back (quite important in order to attach everything to the screen). I choose <em><a href="https://www.amazon.fr/gp/product/B098762GVK/ref=ppx_yo_dt_b_asin_title_o09_s00?ie=UTF8&amp;th=1">HMTECH Tactile 10,1” 1024 x 600</a>.</em></li>
  <li>Battery: It was not clear for me what will be my power requirements in general. So I decided to use an external battery laying around, 20000 mAh capacity, for now. There is some estimations for the power consumption of the Raspberry Pi, but I had no clue how much power the screen will consume.</li>
  <li>Cables: I didn’t even consider this, but it will play a important role later.</li>
  <li>Creality Ender 3 v2 3D printer: to print any required parts.</li>
</ul>

<h1 id="software">Software</h1>

<ul>
  <li>Operating system: my main requirement is to use a Linux distribution, preferably Debian (since I am familiar with its packaging system). I choose Raspberry Pi OS 32-bit
    <ul>
      <li>Yes, I can hear you asking: why the fuck did I do that? honestly, I don’t know :D I had hopes.</li>
      <li>The main reason for using Linux is I know how to build my own programs on it when I need so.</li>
    </ul>
  </li>
  <li>FreeCAD for the design of any required parts.</li>
</ul>

<h1 id="steps">Steps</h1>

<p>My philosophy in general is not to focus too much on getting things right from the first time (a plague in current engineering unfortunately), but to get a whole pipeline, end-to-end, working ASAP, and then iterate over this pipeline (improvements, adding/removing modules, …etc). I’ve been heavily criticized for that approach over the years, but time and time again, it always worked perfectly. Iterations of design, deploy and feedback were always perfect. It is my main way to understand the problem in a deep manner (I need to get my hands dirty). Most of the time, the problem statement/definition is vague at best, or doesn’t even exist. This definitely applies to this project.</p>

<h2 id="round-0-happy-with-the-new-toys">Round 0: happy with the new toys</h2>

<p><a href="https://osm3000.files.wordpress.com/2022/03/img_20220302_134703403-1.jpg"><img src="https://osm3000.files.wordpress.com/2022/03/img_20220302_134703403-1.jpg?w=1024" alt="" /></a></p>

<p>Day 1: get all the parts. The PI Zero W (with the red base) was still part of the planning</p>

<p>Getting everything up and running was quite straightforward. Connect the screen to the PI, the PI to the power source, and Voila!</p>

<p><a href="https://osm3000.files.wordpress.com/2022/03/274078076_1320842185084755_597342884531825599_n1-1.jpg"><img src="https://osm3000.files.wordpress.com/2022/03/274078076_1320842185084755_597342884531825599_n1-1.jpg?w=1024" alt="" /></a></p>

<p>The whole thing is easy to setup in no time</p>

<p>At the beginning, I did connect the USB port of the screen directly to the power. The screen worked, but the touch capability was not there. After some time worrying, I realized that the USB should be connected to the PI directly. It will draw the power from the PI, and send the touch commands to the PI.</p>

<p>With that, many issues became apparent:</p>

<ol>
  <li>The obvious question at that moment was: how to make this whole thing compact?
    <ol>
      <li>Where/How to attach the battery and the Rasbperry Pi to the screen?
        <ol>
          <li>For the PI, luckily, the screen had a mount for it on the back</li>
        </ol>
      </li>
      <li>What to do with the huge space that the cables are consuming?</li>
    </ol>
  </li>
  <li>The screen brightness: It was glowing like the hot sun in the middle of the summer.</li>
  <li>While the touch worked, it was clear that it doesn’t</li>
  <li>Rotating the screen: in the spirit of using it as an e-reader, I would love to have the screen in portrait orientation instead of a landscape. While this is easy in</li>
  <li>All the components are exposed: Even after mounting everything, how can I protect them?
    <ol>
      <li>The driver</li>
      <li>The PI</li>
      <li>The ribbon cables connecting the screen to the PI</li>
    </ol>
  </li>
</ol>

<h2 id="round-1-i-hate-my-life">Round 1: I hate my life</h2>

<p>While thinking about how to resolve all of these issues, I decided that I need to use it more often, in order to get use it.</p>

<p>One day early morning, I took the whole thing, set it up on the table, and started reading. I genuinely hated it. My eyes hurt from the screen. The whole thing is cumbersome.</p>

<p>Since I was still in the touch-based usage mentality, I downloaded a virtual keyboard on the OS. Well, that was hilarious!</p>

<!-- ![](images/img_20220326_173155374_hdr-1.jpg) -->
<p><img src="https://osm3000.files.wordpress.com/2022/03/onscreen-keyboard-raspberry-pi.webp" alt="" />
What the virtual keyboard is supposed to look like.</p>

<p><img src="https://osm3000.files.wordpress.com/2022/03/img_20220326_173155374_hdr-1.jpg" alt="" />
The keyboard I have…No numbers, no arrows, any control button :(</p>

<p>Also, the icons is quite small, and the heat box is not exactly under my finger. It is not straightforward to click ‘X’ to close a window.</p>

<ul>
  <li>This gave me a huge appreciation for what Apple and Samsung did in their phones. There is a good reason why you would need a tight end-to-end control over the software and the hardware, in order to produce a good product. For example, with a proper icons sizing and arrangement of functionality in the OS/software, non of this would have been important.</li>
</ul>

<p>Many hours later, trying to find a way to configure/change this, but to no avail… I considered this to be a dead-end.</p>

<p>I relied on PC keyboard and mouse from that moment on order to control the device. That was cumbersome: the keyboard is almost double the size of the tablet, and the tons of wires.</p>

<p>Since the whole setup was massive (tons of long/rigid cables), I had to connect/disconnect everything for each time I use the tablet (in order to be able to store it).</p>

<p>I designed a single-piece enclosure for the tablet. I spent so many hours on it (because I was very rusty in drawing in 3-D and the software): places for the PI, Driver, and a whole level for the battery and any other component. Time to print an example (it is important to print a demo, to make sure the dimensions are correct, before committing to the final thing)…just to discover it is larger than the printer! After some adjustment in the positioning of the piece, the demo will take…a day and half to print. Clearly this is not going to work…</p>

<p>After I overcome my hate to myself, I listed the following issues to address:</p>

<ol>
  <li>For the enclosure: it is time to print it on several pieces, and fasten them together if necessary. These pieces are: the cover for the PI, the driver and the mount for the battery.</li>
  <li>Keyboard and mouse: After some thinking, I realize I actually don’t like the touch screens in general, especially when I need to write on them. So, I decided to get a mini-keyboard with a touch-pad. I ordered two to evaluate which will work for me.</li>
  <li>The cables: after some discussions with my flatmates, I got introduced to the world of 90/180 degrees cables. After a long digging on amazon, I settled on new set of cables (<a href="https://www.amazon.fr/gp/product/B07BC5XT4P/ref=ppx_yo_dt_b_asin_title_o06_s01?ie=UTF8&amp;psc=1">USB</a>, <a href="https://www.amazon.fr/gp/product/B07VLDS77G/ref=ppx_yo_dt_b_asin_title_o07_s01?ie=UTF8&amp;psc=1">HDMI</a>), and shorter lengths (just to fit the design).</li>
</ol>

<h2 id="round-2-massive-improvements">Round 2: Massive improvements</h2>

<ul>
  <li>With the new cables installed, the whole thing became much much more compact. There was no reason anymore to dismantle anything after use.</li>
  <li>The <a href="https://www.amazon.fr/gp/product/B01N76LDZH/ref=ppx_yo_dt_b_asin_title_o03_s00?ie=UTF8&amp;psc=1">Bluetooth keyboard</a> really made a massive change. It doesn’t use a dongle. The feeling is good. A bit unfamiliar layout, but I got used to it quickly.</li>
  <li>I didn’t realize before I can connect two Bluetooth devices in the same time. When I connected my headphones as well, that was another improvement.
    <ul>
      <li>Since I am using the Raspberry Pi 4, there is an audio jack. But by now, I’ve developed an allergy from seeing cables.</li>
    </ul>
  </li>
  <li>The enclosure: I focused on the protecting the PI at the moment. After many failures (bad measurements, new adherence problems between the filament and the bed of the 3D printer), I finally managed to get it done.</li>
  <li>Software setup: I invested time to add the software I wanted (like VScode), setting up my preferences, SSH keys,…etc. It now became much more usable. Changing the style, colors, all of that, helped a lot to feel “this is mine and I can use it”</li>
</ul>

<p><img src="https://osm3000.files.wordpress.com/2022/03/275720407_653054409103252_6805556995924280321_n-1.jpg?w=1024" alt="" /></p>

<p>Much less cables than before. HDMI remains a challenge (rigid cable, hard to find the right length), but for now it is okay. The PI enclosure works!</p>

<p><img src="https://osm3000.files.wordpress.com/2022/03/275699160_508116540709541_8413618761133755527_n-1.jpg?w=533" alt="" /></p>

<p>Not so thick finally</p>

<p><img src="https://osm3000.files.wordpress.com/2022/03/275230078_1098426160979958_8478573957180597664_n-1.jpg?w=1024" alt="" /></p>

<p>First time I try the new keyboard and the headphones…it was a couple of hours of pure happiness and satisfaction :))</p>

<p>When I connected it everything together, I listened to some music. It was one of the happiest in my life :) It is hard to explain. I was just…satisfied :)</p>

<h2 id="round-3-finishing-the-parts">Round 3: Finishing the parts</h2>

<p>With the previous phase done, I moved on to make the cover for the screen driver circuit. While it is a similar process to the PI’s cover, there was an essential question about where/how the battery would fit. There are only two ways to attach the battery in the back: either by a glue, or some holder that will make use of the only fasteners available (the PI’s and the screen driver). I am not in favor of gluing expensive components, so fasteners it is. But that means that the screen driver design has to take this into account.</p>

<p>After so many brainstorming sessions and discussions with my flatmates, I finally decided…to not attach the battery. It was heavy (thus, a lot to think about in the design of its holder) and I wasn’t yet so sure yet where this whole project is going. Plus, it didn’t see to be a big deal to have the battery separated. It allowed for plugging in to the electric socket quite easily when at home, when battery is not needed (thus, saving the battery’s life).</p>

<p>I also made two supports/holders for the tablets. These made a huge improvement in the whole experience.</p>

<p><a href="https://osm3000.files.wordpress.com/2022/04/img_20220322_182431902.jpg"><img src="https://osm3000.files.wordpress.com/2022/04/img_20220322_182431902.jpg?w=1024" alt="" /></a></p>

<p>Much better organized setup now!</p>

<p><a href="https://osm3000.files.wordpress.com/2022/04/img_20220322_170943540-1.jpg"><img src="https://osm3000.files.wordpress.com/2022/04/img_20220322_170943540-1.jpg?w=1024" alt="" /></a></p>

<p>The new supports…neat :)</p>

<p><a href="https://osm3000.files.wordpress.com/2022/04/img_20220322_170957172.jpg"><img src="https://osm3000.files.wordpress.com/2022/04/img_20220322_170957172.jpg?w=1024" alt="" /></a></p>

<h2 id="round-4-getting-out-of-the-housewill-it-break">Round 4: Getting out of the house…will it break?</h2>

<p>That was an important challenge, and I hesitated on starting it a lot. But finally, I did. The only thing that had to be dismantled with the screen USB connection to the RaspberryPi (otherwise, there will be too much pressure on this part).</p>

<p>The whole thing WORKED :D I was super happy. Easy to setup, convenient to work with. I went many times for coffee shops. Even did a lot of small codes on it.</p>

<p>I was more happy when I came home, and it still worked fine :)</p>

<h2 id="round-5-multiple-days-stress-testing">Round 5: Multiple days stress testing</h2>

<p>You might have read my previous post about analyzing articles from LeMonde. Well, I am preparing for phase two, which includes scrapping ~1.25 MILLION article.</p>

<p>Let’s use the tablet to do a part of the job.</p>

<p>For 1 week straight, no breaks, the tablet was assigned the job of scrapping this data from LeMonde. Aside from dust on the screen, everything works perfectly!</p>

<h1 id="lessons-for-the-future">Lessons for the future</h1>

<ol>
  <li>Getting something functional and running these days is quite easy. Getting something usable is much more difficult.
    <ol>
      <li>Details matters. The fact that you can easily carry it, operate it, handle it, really matters. For example, the support/holders that I made, or the bluetooth mini-keyboard, both improved a lot the usability.</li>
    </ol>
  </li>
  <li>I didn’t realize there are <a href="https://www.aliexpress.com/wholesale?catId=0&amp;initiative_id=AS_20220406122434&amp;SearchText=ink+display">large ink-screen available (AliExpress)</a>!! Definitely I should have checked there first before I made a decision about the screen.</li>
  <li>Get a screen that you can control its brightness! Good screen matters a lot.</li>
  <li>Components in France are just ridiculously expensive (give examples: cables, screen, screws). For such a project, it would have been better to order everything from AliExpress. The main issue was time (the delivery time of AliExpress is quite long, and I was in a hurry). But, lesson for the future.</li>
  <li>Raspberry PI is a game changer. And I think the whole move towards mini-computers like this is just fucking awesome in general. Having that much capability (computing, memory, peripherals, interfaces, connectivity) out of the box has saved enormous amount of time</li>
  <li>For the enclosure, I think that for a large flat surface, I am convinced that starting from a sheet of wood/acrylic glass will be the best choice. 3D printing such a surface is problematic (need a large printer, or need to print it in sections and fasten them together). Adding mounts/supports on that sheet for other components can be done with the 3D printers. I am resisting the urge to buy a CNC machine right now :D, but I can definitely see the problems it can solve. Plus, I would love to use acrylic glass (I love to make the electronics and the lights visible). This is an adventure for another time.</li>
  <li>While the ad-hoc benchmark that I did for the power consumption was very promising (low power consumption, very suitable to use external batteries), I noticed that, during the boot sequence, sometimes the whole thing just shuts-down. My hypotheses were either something is damaged, or there is a power surge near the end of the boot sequence. I removed the monitor (assuming that it is its fault), gave time to the PI to boot, then connected the monitor, but it didn’t boot correctly!<br />
 Finally, I tried multiple power adapters and batteries. It seems to work only with the high-quality ones. So, the lesson here is: a good quality adapter / battery is a must.</li>
  <li>Go for a 64-bit OS from the beginning :D</li>
</ol>

<h1 id="what-is-next">What is next?</h1>

<ol>
  <li>What to do about the battery? I don’t know for sure yet. Should I keep it as it is now, with the battery separated from the device? Should I group some battery cells together, create</li>
  <li>Make a phone: For me, the phone is my most used computer, and the least controlled one in terms of programmability and upgradability. It will pose a challenge to make it small and compact enough to be usable, but I am curious about this journey to discover what I really want and like, without the previously imposed biases from the current manufactures.</li>
  <li>Get/build very customized and small cables: To get the size even smaller, and mobility higher, I need to take another look at the cables. Either I will make them from scratch (which I am not very eager to do at the moment), or find some alternatives. Not a deal breaker at the moment though.</li>
</ol>

<h1 id="acknowledgement">Acknowledgement</h1>

<p>Many thanks for <a href="https://www.linkedin.com/in/dominic-algernon-wallis-123b42187/">Dom Wallis</a>, <a href="https://www.linkedin.com/in/juliette-jaupitre/">Juliette Jaupitre</a>, <a href="https://www.linkedin.com/in/firasmourad/">Firas Mourad</a>, for their inputs, suggestions, and encouragement :)</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="electronics" /><category term="engineering" /><category term="thinking" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Over the last couple of years, I came to the conclusion that I need to have a higher degree of control over my environment:]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">A view on France - Part 1</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/data-science/machine-learning/nlp/2022/02/15/french-journey-part-1.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="A view on France - Part 1" /><published>2022-02-15T23:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2022-02-15T23:00:00+01:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/data-science/machine-learning/nlp/2022/02/15/french-journey-part-1</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/data-science/machine-learning/nlp/2022/02/15/french-journey-part-1.html"><![CDATA[<p>For whatever reason, even though I live in France for ~8 years now, I still struggle with learning French. My environment is always in English all the time, and all my French friends speak good English as well. To my surprise, speaking French is not a deal breaker as I once thought.</p>

<p><a href="https://github.com/osm3000/Language-Analysis">All the code used in this analysis can be fine here</a>.</p>

<h2 id="solutions-that-itried">Solutions that I tried</h2>

<p>The road started normally, with dreams that working hard will do the trick, and that this problem is pretty much solved long time ago. Unfortunately, that proved to be not the case — for me at least. I tried:</p>

<ul>
  <li>Apps like Babbel and Duolingo: Incredibly frustrating experience. Words that doesn’t seem to be used anywhere else. Whatever progress I make in the app (and trust me, I did a lot of progress) doesn’t seem to translate into reality at all. I don’t feel my comprehension or my ability to speak improved in any significant manner after few months of regular use of these apps. </li>
  <li>Listening to TV series and programs: I just don’t like TV series or reality shows or any of that in general. It didn’t take long before I stopped this direction. </li>
  <li>Listening to podcasts/videos on my favorite topics: mainly technical interests. That was quite helpful for sometime. It is a passive activity though.</li>
  <li>Community teachers: in platforms like <a href="https://www.italki.com/">italki</a>. A lot of progress were made there, but it is not easy to find enough good teachers or sustainable appointments. My objective was 1 hour of French everyday. No one teacher could satisfy this requirement. I ended up between 4~5 amazing teachers, but it is hard to coordinate and reserve the time. It was always a complex optimization problem.</li>
  <li>Courses in language centers: it was always incredibly expensive, hard to find on short notice, inflexible time slots that doesn’t fit with my work.</li>
</ul>

<p>In short, no luck :( </p>

<h2 id="time-for-the-technical-hammer">Time for the technical hammer</h2>

<p>My idea is to try to systematically understand what are the characteristics of the French language really is, and use that to design a data-driven curriculum for myself.</p>

<p>To understand the French language, I decided to analyze the articles in LeMonde newspaper. I scrapped a considerable amount of corpus, ~13K articles, from different domains. Using some basic NLP and frequency analyses, I am hoping to reach some insights about what the language is, that can enhance the quality of my decisions.</p>

<p>When analyzing the verbs, I decided to convert all the verbs to their original form (the simple present). Otherwise, it creates a lot of unnecessary clutter in the analysis.</p>

<h2 id="overview-on-theresults">Overview on the results</h2>

<p><a href="https://osm3000.files.wordpress.com/2022/02/wordcloud_allwords.png"><img src="https://osm3000.files.wordpress.com/2022/02/wordcloud_allwords.png?w=1024" alt="" /></a></p>

<p>Word-cloud for all the words</p>

<p>One can see that verbs like <em>avoir</em>, <em>etre</em>, and connectors like <em>qui</em>, <em>que</em>, <em>et</em> and <em>il</em> are the highest recurring words in the French language.</p>

<p>Let’s take a closer look at separate categories of those words: adverbs, verbs and nouns.</p>

<ul>
  <li>
    <p><img src="https://osm3000.files.wordpress.com/2022/02/wordcloud_alladverbs.png?w=1024" alt="" /></p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p><img src="https://osm3000.files.wordpress.com/2022/02/wordcloud_allverbs.png?w=1024" alt="" /></p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p><img src="https://osm3000.files.wordpress.com/2022/02/wordcloud_allnouns.png?w=1024" alt="" /></p>
  </li>
</ul>

<p>My personal interest is to convert these words into flashcards, and based on their frequency and importance (I will tackle the <em>importance</em> part later), I can focus on what really matter.</p>

<p>Although not a quantitative analysis, if you ever used tools like Babbel or Duolingo before, you might notice that there is an asymmetry between their words and those words. For example, on of the things you learn at the beginning in those applications are words like: garcon, fille, fils, pere, mere, ….etc, but you can notice that none of those words appears in those in big font in those word-clouds. </p>

<h3 id="how-many-articles-should-i-read">How many articles should I read?</h3>

<p>Another issue of interest for me is: how many articles I do need to read in order to have been exposed to most of the words? I rephrased this problem in what I call the ‘insertion speed’: how much each article contribute with new unique words? </p>

<p>The way I did it was not a comprehensive/realistic method in my opinion, but a fast and a quick lower-limit indicator. Basically, for each article, I measured how many words I didn’t see before, then add those new words to my seen-words-list, and move on to the next article, …etc. I ordered the resulting list — since it is noisy — in order to get a sense of what we are talking about.</p>

<p><a href="https://osm3000.files.wordpress.com/2022/02/insertionspeedordered.png"><img src="https://osm3000.files.wordpress.com/2022/02/insertionspeedordered.png?w=1024" alt="" /></a></p>

<p>One can see that, with around ~500 article, there is barely any new word added to the seen words. </p>

<p>What I really like about the insertion speed is that it could be a way to manage my personal training procedure. If I’ve a system that is aware of the words I know so far (through articles I read, or manually inserted words), the system can then keep suggesting articles, in the area of interest, that either focus on older vocabulary (to enhance it), thus, having a small-to-no insertion speed, or to focus on learning new words, thus, asking the system for articles with higher insertion speed. </p>

<p>This could be more beneficial, since it changes the personal training system from the sole focus on flashcards, to article-based learning (you will learn new words by reading the articles mentioning those words).</p>

<p>With a large enough repertoire of articles — and even an easy manner to add new articles — I can definitely imagine a pretty good training procedure.</p>

<h4 id="word-frequencies">Word Frequencies</h4>

<p>What is really fascinating for me is the quantification of the long-tail phenomena in French (spoiler alert: MASSIVE long tail). To get an idea, let’s look at some numbers.</p>

<div class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge"><div class="highlight"><pre class="highlight"><code>Total Number of words seen: ~7.6M words
Number of unique words: ~116K words
10% of the total words seen is just 3 unique words
20% of the total words seen is just 17 unique words
50% of the total words seen is just 375 unique words
80% of the total words seen is just 2624 unique words
90$ of the total words seen is just 6506 unique words
</code></pre></div></div>

<p>Even though the long-tail phenomena is expected, it is still mind-blowing for me to see it in action like this.</p>

<p>While aggregation is always amazing to get a good overview over the topic, it’s interesting to dive deeper and see more specific details. Let’s look at the same stats, but for verbs, nouns, and adverbs</p>

<p>Verbs</p>

<div class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge"><div class="highlight"><pre class="highlight"><code>Total Number of words seen: ~1.2M verb
Number of unique words: ~11.5K verb
10% of the total verbs seen is just 3 unique verb
20% of the total verbs seen is just 14 unique verb
50% of the total verbs seen is just 139 unique verb
80% of the total verbs seen is just 585 unique verb
90% of the total verbs seen is just 1117 unique verb
</code></pre></div></div>

<p>Nouns</p>

<div class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge"><div class="highlight"><pre class="highlight"><code>Total Number of words seen: ~2.8M noun
Number of unique words: ~41.6K noun
10% of the total verbs seen is just 27 unique noun
20% of the total verbs seen is just 77 unique noun
50% of the total verbs seen is just 408 unique noun
80% of the total verbs seen is just 1731 unique noun
90% of the total verbs seen is just 3599 unique noun
</code></pre></div></div>

<p>Adverbs</p>

<div class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge"><div class="highlight"><pre class="highlight"><code>Total Number of words seen: ~604K adverb
Number of unique words: ~3.4K adverb
10% of the total verbs seen is just 0 !! unique adverb
20% of the total verbs seen is just 1 unique adverb
50% of the total verbs seen is just 11 unique adverb
80% of the total verbs seen is just 49 unique adverb
90% of the total verbs seen is just 94 unique adverb
</code></pre></div></div>

<p>All-in-all, assuming that being good at French is about mastering <strong>80%</strong> of the words, then I should focus on the <strong>2624</strong> words for the moment, over <strong>2/3</strong> of them are nouns and less than <strong>1/3</strong> are verbs. I can easily now transfer this into flash-cards, and dig into them :)</p>

<p>These are the links for those lists: <a href="https://github.com/osm3000/Language-Analysis/blob/main/results/noFilter/allWords.csv">all words</a>, <a href="https://github.com/osm3000/Language-Analysis/blob/main/results/noFilter/allVerbs.csv">verbs</a>, <a href="https://github.com/osm3000/Language-Analysis/blob/main/results/noFilter/allNouns.csv">nouns</a> and <a href="https://github.com/osm3000/Language-Analysis/blob/main/results/noFilter/allAdverbs.csv">adverbs</a>. Maybe you can use them for your own application :)</p>

<h2 id="origin-of-thedata">Origin of the data</h2>

<p>I have built my database by scraping <a href="https://www.lemonde.fr/"><em>LeMonde</em></a> articles. After some investigation, I realized that the articles are organized in categories, in the form of </p>

<div class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge"><div class="highlight"><pre class="highlight"><code>https://www.lemonde.fr/&lt;category&gt;
</code></pre></div></div>

<p>The categories are so many, and it is not clear how to get a comprehensive list of them — or if that is the best approach. But, one can at least enumerate some of the interesting categories from the navigation bar. A better way would have been to parse the <a href="https://www.lemonde.fr/archives-du-monde/">archive of LeMonde</a>.</p>

<p>Within each article, you can look for the following tags in order to get the relevant information in the HTML source:</p>

<div class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge"><div class="highlight"><pre class="highlight"><code>&lt;description&gt; : &lt;tag type&gt; - &lt;class name&gt;
Author name: span - author__name
Article description: p - article__desc
Article paragraphs: p - article__paragraph
Image links: figure &gt; img - &lt;No class name&gt;
Image captions figure &gt; figcaption - &lt;No class name&gt;
</code></pre></div></div>

<p>You should be able to scrap any article you like immediately with this info :)</p>

<p>To support the work of the journalists in LeMonde, I made a subscription in LeMonde. An added advantage is to get access to the full premium articles. Without a subscription however, using the same script, I can access the free part of the premium articles (almost 1/3 of the article).</p>

<h2 id="conclusion">Conclusion</h2>

<p>I started this little exercise out of frustration, and the more I dived into it, the more exciting it turned to be. As potential clear outcomes, one can now:</p>

<ol>
  <li>Make flashcards of the important words, and focus on them, based on the uni-gram/word frequency analysis.</li>
  <li>Prepare an article/application based learning: if I can keep count of the insertion speed, and the current words that I know, and given that I’ve a repertoire of articles, the system can recommend me the next article to read, based on criteria in between the two extreme:
    <ol>
      <li>I want to learn as many new words as possible (max insertion)</li>
      <li>I want to practice what I know only (min/zero insertion)</li>
    </ol>
  </li>
  <li>Analyze the quality of my writing:</li>
</ol>

<p>But one can imagine even more applications here, for example:</p>

<ol>
  <li>Bi-gram/tri-gram analysis: time to focus on making sentences. Single words are interesting and all, but small repetitive pieces of sentences are much more powerful to learn. It will cut the thinking time considerably.</li>
  <li>Importance analysis: with techniques like TF-IDF, what are the important words in French? so far, I focused on the common words only.
    <ol>
      <li>Also perform this analysis per domain. It might help to ease the entry to specific domain (like science, technology, sport, …etc) by getting the key words in that domain.</li>
    </ol>
  </li>
  <li>Cross this data with other data: one topic of interest for me is to understand the politicians and the media, and their inter-relationship. Recently, I got access to Twitter APIs. I would like to go deeper into what the french politicians talk about, their interaction, how and when a story breaks, …etc.</li>
</ol>

<p>I would love to know what you think :)</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="data-science" /><category term="machine-learning" /><category term="nlp" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[For whatever reason, even though I live in France for ~8 years now, I still struggle with learning French. My environment is always in English all the time, and all my French friends speak good English as well. To my surprise, speaking French is not a deal breaker as I once thought.]]></summary></entry></feed>